An epic story of three brothers. Bound by blood.
Divided by fate. Driven by destiny.
Bound by Honor is a crime, action, drama film directed by Taylor Hackford.
Based on the true life experiences of poet Jimmy Santiago Baca, the film focuses
on half-brothers Paco and Cruz, and their bi-racial cousin Miklo.
It opens in 1972, as the three are members of an East L.A.
gang known as the "Vatos Locos", and the story focuses on how a violent
crime and the influence of narcotics alter their lives.
Miklo is incarcerated and sent to San Quentin,
where he makes a "home" for himself.
Cruz becomes an exceptional artist, but a heroin
addiction overcomes him with tragic results.
Paco becomes a cop and an enemy to his "carnal", Miklo.
Miklo, played by Damian Chapa.
Cruz, played by Jesse Borrego.
Paco, played by Benjamin Bratt.
Montana, played by Enrique Castillo.
Magic Mike, played by Victor Rivers.
Bonafide, played by Delroy Lindo.
Blood In Blood Out (also known as Bound by Honor and Blood In Blood Out: Bound By Honor) is a 1993 American epic crime
drama film directed by Taylor Hackford, from a screenplay co-written by Jimmy Santiago Baca  and Floyd Mutrux.
The film follows the intertwining lives of three
Chicano relatives from 1972 to 1984.
They start out as members of a street gang in East Los Angeles, and as dramatic
incidents occur, their lives and friendships are forever changed.
The film stars Jesse Borrego, Benjamin Bratt,
Enrique Castillo, and Damian Chapa.
The screenplay is partly autobiographical, drawn from Baca’s
experiences in street gangs and imprisonment.
The film's title refers to the initiation ritual of having to kill someone to enter a gang
and, on the reverse end, not being able to leave the gang unless killed.
The film was released by Buena Vista Pictures Distribution on April 30, 1993.
Critical reviews were mixed to positive, and Blood In Blood Out was a box office disappointment,
but later became a cult classic film  among parts of the Mexican-American community.
The film explores themes of street gang, ghetto, juvenile prison, artist, jail.
The tone is intense and dark and emotional.